<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1982 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1982.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4387 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4387.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6481 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6481.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6487 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6487.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6488 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6488.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6489 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6489.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7942 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8182 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8182.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8630 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8630.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8488 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8488.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9286 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9286.xml">
<!ENTITY id.draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-crl-numbers SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-crl-numbers-05.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std"
docName="draft-ietf-sidrops-manifest-numbers-05"
ipr="trust200902" updates="RFC9286" consensus="true">

  <front>
    <title>RPKI Manifest Number Handling</title>

    <author initials="T." surname="Harrison" fullname="Tom Harrison">
        <organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>6 Cordelia St</street>
                <city>South Brisbane</city>
                <code>4101</code>
                <country>Australia</country>
                <region>QLD</region>
            </postal>
            <email>tomh@apnic.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George G. Michaelson" initials="G." surname="Michaelson">
	<organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia-Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>

	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street>6 Cordelia St</street>
		<city>South Brisbane</city>
		<region>QLD</region>
		<code>4101</code>
		<country>Australia</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
        <organization></organization>
	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street/>
		<city>Amsterdam</city>
		<region/>
		<country>Netherlands</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>job@sobornost.net</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>template</keyword>
    <abstract>
        <t>

            The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) makes use of
            signed objects called manifests.  A manifest lists each
            file that a publisher intends to include within an RPKI
            repository, and can be used to detect certain forms of
            attack against a repository.  Manifests include a
            "manifest number" (manifestNumber), which the publisher
            must increment whenever it issues a new manifest, and
            Relying Parties (RPs) are required to verify that a
            newly-retrieved manifest for a given Certification
            Authority (CA) has a higher manifestNumber than the
            previously-validated manifest.  However, the
            manifestNumber field is 20 octets in length (i.e. not
            unbounded), and no behaviour is specified for when a
            manifestNumber reaches the largest possible value.  This
            document specifies publisher and RP behaviour for this
            scenario.

        </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>

            The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) <xref
            target="RFC6480" /> makes use of signed objects <xref
            target="RFC6488" /> called manifests <xref
            target="RFC9286" />.  A manifest lists each file that a
            publisher intends to include within an RPKI repository
            <xref target="RFC6481" />, and can be used to detect
            certain forms of attack against a repository.  Manifests
            include a "manifest number" (manifestNumber), which the
            publisher must increment by one whenever it issues a new
            manifest, and Relying Parties (RPs) are required to verify
            that a newly-retrieved manifest for a given Certification
            Authority (CA) has a higher manifestNumber than the
            previously-validated manifest (see <xref
            target="RFC9286" sectionFormat="of" section="4.2.1" />).

        </t>

        <t>

            However, the manifestNumber field is 20 octets in length
            (i.e. not unbounded), and no behaviour is specified for
            when a manifestNumber reaches the largest possible value
            (2<sup>159</sup>-1).  When that value is reached, some RP
            implementations will accept a new manifest for the CA only
            once the current manifest has expired, while others will
            not accept a new manifest at all.  (For the purposes of
            <xref target="RFC9286" />, a "CA" is represented by a CA
            certificate with a stable location and a stable private
            key. Reissuing a CA certificate with changed resources or
            a changed expiry date does not change the identity of the
            CA such that the stored manifestNumber for the CA is
            reset, for example.)

        </t>

        <t>

            While it is practically impossible for a publisher to
            reach the largest possible value under normal operating
            conditions (it would require that the publisher issue one
            manifest per second for 23,171,956,451,847,141,650,870
            quintillion years), there is a chance that it could be
            reached due to bugs in the issuance or publication systems
            or incorrect/inadvertent use of those systems.  For
            example:

            <list>

                <t>Incrementing by large values when issuing
                manifests, such that the time to reach that largest
                value is reduced.</t>

                <t>Reissuing new manifests in an infinite delay-free
                loop, such that the manifestNumber increases by a
                large value in a comparatively short period of
                time.</t>

                <t>Inadvertently setting the manifestNumber to the
                largest possible value, such that the publisher will
                no longer be able to publish usable manifests for that
                repository.</t>

            </list>

            These scenarios might also arise in combination and be more
            severe as a result.  For example, a CA might increase the
            manifest number by a large value on reissuance, and also
            reissue the manifest more frequently than is necessary.

        </t>

        <t>

            For a subordinate CA, the risk of repository invalidation
            due to this problem can be addressed by the publisher
            simply using the key rollover process (<xref
            target="RFC6489" />) to get a new CA certificate.  RPs
            will treat this new certificate as
            though it represents a distinct CA, and the manifestNumber
            can be reset at that point.

        </t>

        <t>

            However, this option is not available for RPKI Trust
            Anchors (TAs).  If a TA publishes a manifest with the
            largest-possible manifestNumber value, then it is
            difficult to rely on the TA after that point, since (per
            earlier comments) some RPs will not accept a new manifest
            until the current one has expired, while others will
            reject all new manifests indefinitely.  Particularly in
            the case of TAs, the manifest validity period may be quite
            long, too.  Issuing a new TA and distributing the
            associated TAL to clients would involve a large amount of
            work for TA operators and RPs.  Additionally, depending on
            the RP implementation being used, there would be a
            limited degree of RPKI protection by way of that TA for
            the time between the issuance of the problematic manifest
            and the installation of the new TAL.

        </t>

        <t>

            In order to avoid these problems, this document defines
            how publishers and RPs can handle this scenario in order
            to facilitate ongoing use of an affected repository.

        </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119" /> <xref target="RFC8174"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="manifest-number-handling" title="Manifest Number Handling">

        <t>

            For a given CA, an RP MUST NOT reject a new manifest
            issued by that CA on the basis of it not having a higher
            manifestNumber than a previously-validated manifest if the
            new manifest has a different filename from that of the
            previously-validated manifest.  In other words, an RP MUST
            reset its stored manifestNumber for a given CA if the CA
            changes the filename of its manifest.

        </t>

        <t>

            With this behaviour, it is possible for a CA to be
            configured such that any time it issues a new manifest, it
            uses a new filename for that manifest.  If a CA were
            configured in this way, the manifestNumber validation set
            out in <xref target="RFC9286" sectionFormat="of"
            section="4.2.1" /> would have no purpose.  To avoid this
            outcome, CAs SHOULD NOT use new filenames for manifests
            except in situations where it is necessary to ensure the
            ongoing validity of the CA or its repository.  Similarly,
            RP software SHOULD alert its operators when a manifest
            filename changes for a given CA.

        </t>

        <t>

            To avoid certain forms of replay attack, the RP MUST
            verify that the URI in the accessLocation in one of the
            id-ad-signedObject accessMethods in the manifest's Subject
            Information Access (SIA) extension exactly matches the URI
            presented in the RPKI Repository Delta Protocol (RRDP)
            <xref target="RFC8182" /> "publish" element or the path
            presented by remote rsync servers.

        </t>

        <t>

            <xref target="RFC6481" sectionFormat="of" section="2.2" />
            contains non-normative guidance for the naming of manifest
            files in repositories.  While a CA that supports the
            behaviour described in this section cannot preserve the
            exact filename suggested by that text (per <xref
            target="RFC4387" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1" />), the
            CA SHOULD still ensure that the filename is a value
            derived from the public key of the CA, per the more
            general guidance in that section.

        </t>

        <t>

            A CA specifies its manifest URI by way of an SIA entry
            with an accessMethod of id-ad-rpkiManifest (<xref
            target="RFC6487" />).  For the purposes of this document,
            the manifest filename is the final segment of the path of
            the accessLocation URI from that SIA entry.

        </t>

        <t>

            <xref target="RFC6487" sectionFormat="of"
            section="4.8.8.1" /> states that a CA may include in its
            certificate multiple id-ad-rpkiManifest SIA entries.  For
            comparisons, the RP may use the filename from any one of
            the id-ad-rpkiManifest SIA entries in the
            previously-validated CA certificate.  If that filename
            does not appear in any of the id-ad-rpkiManifest SIA
            entries in the CA certificate that is currently being
            validated, then the manifest filename has changed, for the
            purposes of this section.  The corollary of this behaviour
            is that a CA that includes multiple id-ad-rpkiManifest SIA
            entries in its certificate and wants to rely on the
            behaviour defined in this document MUST ensure that none
            of the manifest filenames in the previous CA certificate
            appear in the newly-issued CA certificate.

        </t>
         
        <t>

            Note that the approach set out in this section is
            different from that described in <xref target="RFC8488"
            sectionFormat="of" section="3.2.1"/>.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="general-repository-handling" title="General Repository Handling">

        <t>

            The previous section contains a specific update for the
            handling of manifest numbers, in order to address one
            potential permanent invalidity scenario.  RPs that
            encounter other permanent invalidity scenarios SHOULD also
            consider how those can be addressed such that the scenario
            does not require the relevant CA or TA to perform a key
            rollover operation.  For example, in the event that an RP
            recognises that a permanent invalidity scenario has
            occurred, the RP could alert the operator and provide an
            option to the operator to stop relying on cached data for
            the affected repository, so that the CA can rectify the
            problem.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations">

        <t>

            CA software may opt to support the manifest number reset
            functionality in various ways.  For example, it could
            change the manifest filename when the manifestNumber
            reaches a certain threshold, or it could alert the
            operator in this scenario and request confirmation that
            the filename should be changed.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
            The RPKI primarily exists to support and improve security of the global Internet routing system.
        </t>
        <t>
            Reliability improvements to the RPKI itself, such as outlined in this document, strengthen its dependability (see <xref target="RFC6480" section="8"/>).
        </t>
        <t>
            <xref target="RFC9286"/> requires that RPs perform two replay-related checks on newly-retrieved manifests: firstly, that the purported new manifest has a greater manifestNumber than the cached manifest, and secondly, that the purported new manifest has a more recent thisUpdate than the cached manifest.
            An RP that implements the behaviour in Section 2 will momentarily omit the manifestNumber check following a manifest filename change.
            So long as the RP still performs the second check described above, it will be protected against replay attacks.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>

            This document has no actions for IANA.

        </t>
    </section>

    <section removeInRFC="true">
      <name>Implementation status</name>
      <t>
        This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref target="RFC7942" />.
        The description of implementations in this section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing drafts to RFCs.
        Please note that the listing of any individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
        Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.
        This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their features.
        Readers are advised to note that other implementations may exist.
      </t>
      <t>
        According to <xref target="RFC7942" />, "this will allow reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature.
        It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as they see fit".
      </t>

      <ul>
        <li>
          OpenBSD <xref target="rpki-client"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          Routinator <xref target="routinator"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>

            The authors would like to thank <contact fullname="Theo
            Buehler"/>, <contact fullname="Ben Maddison" />, <contact
            fullname="Rob Austein" />, <contact fullname="Tim
            Bruijnzeels" />, and <contact fullname="Russ Housley" />
            for their review and feedback on this document.

        </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC4387;
      &RFC6487;
      &RFC6488;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC8182;
      &RFC9286;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1982;
      &RFC5280;
      &RFC6480;
      &RFC6481;
      &RFC6489;
      &RFC7942;
      &RFC8630;
      &RFC8488;
      &id.draft-ietf-sidrops-rpki-crl-numbers;
      <reference anchor="rpki-client" target="https://www.rpki-client.org/">
        <front>
          <title>rpki-client</title>
            <author>
            <organization>OpenBSD Project</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2024" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="routinator" target="https://www.nlnetlabs.nl/projects/routing/routinator/">
        <front>
          <title>Routinator</title>
            <author>
            <organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2024" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Serial Number Arithmetic">

        <t>

            Serial number arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982" /> is an
            approach that has been used in the DNS context (among
            others) to permit the indefinite use of a finite number
            space.  At least in theory, it would be possible to use a
            similar approach with the manifestNumber field as well.

        </t>

        <t>

            However, unlike the corresponding DNS context with Start
            of Authority (SOA) resource records, an RPKI CA does not
            have visibility into or control over RPKI RPs generally.
            This means that it is not possible to select an updated
            manifestNumber value or to manage the relevant state
            transitions so as to guarantee that all RPs will have
            valid state at the end of the process.  The approach
            proposed in <xref target="manifest-number-handling" />
            does not have this problem.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Manifest thisUpdate">

        <t>

            The thisUpdate field in the manifest object is of type
            GeneralizedTime, defined in <xref target="RFC5280"
            sectionFormat="of" section="4.1.2.5.2" />.  This type has
            a maximum value of 99991231235959Z (i.e. 31 December 9999
            23:59:59 GMT).  <xref target="RFC9286" sectionFormat="of"
            section="4.2.1" /> requires that "[e]ach RP MUST verify
            that this field value is greater (more recent) than the
            most recent manifest it has validated", so it would appear
            to be subject to the same problem as for manifest numbers.
            However, during validation, if the RP detects that the
            current time is not between the manifest thisUpdate and
            nextUpdate values, the RP must treat the fetch as a failed
            fetch.  Therefore, the RP will not cache a manifest with a
            current date far in the future, and the CA can rectify the
            problem here by reissuing the relevant manifest with the
            correct date.

        </t>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
